Charles Seymour, Jr. Collection of European Sculpture, Painting and Architecture Photographs and Research Materials
Yale University Arts Library
Charles Seymour, Jr. Collection of European Sculpture, Painting and Architecture Photographs and Research Materials
1950-1970
VRC 325
Yale University Arts Library
11.9
23 boxes
Research photographs, correspondence, notes, and typescripts of Charles Seymour Jr. deposited in the Visual Resources Collection upon his death in 1977. This collection is comprised of study and publication photographs principally associated with Seymour's Pelican History of Art Volume: Sculpture in Italy, 1400-1500, Baltimore, 1st ed. 1966. Additional materials are associated with his research on Noyon Cathedral as well as a wide array of interests in European post-Renaissance sculpture. The boxed collection reflects the arrangement and order of the storage cabinets in the Visual Resources Collection at the time of its transfer to the Library Shelving Facility in 2008. Although the material may have been reorganized several times, the arrangement appears to reflect the order in which the material was received from the office of Charles Seymour, Jr. Many photographs are Alinari stock or major monuments within Charles Seymour's areas of expertise.
Seymour, Charles, Jr., 1912-1977
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Research photographs, correspondence, notes, and typescripts of Charles Seymour Jr. deposited in the Visual Resources Collection upon his death in 1977. This collection is comprised of study and publication photographs principally associated with Seymour's Pelican History of Art Volume: Sculpture in Italy, 1400-1500, Baltimore, 1st ed. 1966. Additional materials are associated with his research on Noyon Cathedral as well as a wide array of interests in European post-Renaissance sculpture. The boxed collection reflects the arrangement and order of the storage cabinets in the Visual Resources Collection at the time of its transfer to the Library Shelving Facility in 2008. Although the material may have been reorganized several times, the arrangement appears to reflect the order in which the material was received from the office of Charles Seymour, Jr. Many photographs are Alinari stock or major monuments within Charles Seymour's areas of expertise.
Arrangement
In folders, arranged thematically and alphabetically.
Arts, European; Photographs; Reproductions
- Bologna, Palazzo Pubblico (Box 1)
- Emila, General (Box 1)
- Mazzoni. Emilia, Modena (Box 1)
- Mazzoni, Varia (Box 1)
- Mazzoni, Modena Cathedral (Box 1)
- Mazzoni, Ferrrar (Box 1)
- Mazzoni, Reggio Emilia (Box 1)
- Mazzoni, Brescia (Box 1)
- Niccolo dell'Arca (Box 1)
- North Italian Bronzes (Box 1)
- Padua, General (Box 1)
- Padua, Bellano (Box 1)
- Padua, Riccio (Box 1)
- Padua, S. Giustina (Box 1)
- Verona, S. Anastasia (Box 1)
- Verona, S. Giovanni in Fonte (Box 1)
- Siena, Vecchietta (Box 2)
- Lorenzo Mairani (Box 2)
- Late Follower of Maitani (Box 2)
- Giovanni d'Agostino (Box 2)
- Giovanni Pisano (Box 2)
- Lando di Pietro (Box 2)
- Siena, Cozzarelli (Box 2)
- Siena, Neroccio (Box 2)
- Siena, Francesco di Giorgio (Box 2)
- Siena, Antonio Federighi (Box 2)
- Mino da Fiesole (Box 2)
- General Bronzes (Box 2)
- 15th Century Artist's Portraits (Box 2)
- Florence, Ornament (Box 2)
- Female Portrait Busts (Box 2)
- S. Vivaldi Osservanti (Box 2)
- Perugia, Porta Principale (Box 2)
- Arezzo, Cathedral (Box 2)
- Laurana (Box 2)
- Francesco di Simone Ferrucci (Box 2)
- 15th-Century Italian Sculptor's Drawings (Box 2)
- Provincial (Box 2)
- Wood Sculpture, West Tuscany (Box 2)
- Prato, Maso di Bartolommeo (Box 2)
- Urbino, Sculpture 15th Century (Box 2)
- Urbino, Domenico Rosselli (Box 2)
- Urbino, Il Greco (Michele di Giovanni da Fiesole) (Box 2)
- Master of the Marble Madonnas (Box 2)
- 15th Century, General (Box 2)
- Siena, Valdambrino (Box 2)
- Ancona, S. Ciriaco (Duomo). Tomb of Beato Gianelli (Box 3)
- Milan (Box 3)
- 14th-15th Century Italy (Box 3)
- Lombardy, amadeo (Pavia, Cremona, Isola Bella) (Box 3)
- Lombardy, Pavia (Box 3)
- Lombardy, Milan, Bergamo, Como (Box 3)
- Naples (Box 3)
- Sicily (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano, Chapel of the Arts (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano, Ancestor's Chapel (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano, Cappella dei Giuochi Infantile (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano, Chapels of St. Michael and the Virgin (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano, Chapel of the Planets (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano, Tomb of Sigismondo Malatesta, Tomb of Isotta (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano, Cappella di S. Sigismondo (Box 3)
- Agostino di Duccio (Box 3)
- Rimini, Tempio Malatestiano, PortaL, Cappella delle Reliquie; Portal, Cella della Vergine; Cella delle Reliquie; Cella della Vergine; Cella della Madonna dell'Acqua (Box 4)
- Perugia, San Bernardino (Box 4)
- Agostino di Duccio, Perugia, S. Demenico; Museo; S. Lorenzo (Box 4)
- Agostino di Duccio, Madonna Reliefs, Louvre, Bargello, National Gallery of Art Naples (Box 4)
- Naples, Arch of Alfonso of Aragon (Box 4)
- Niccolo di Guardiagrele (Box 4)
- Sulmona (Box 4)
- Andrea dell'Aquila (Box 4)
- Ancona, Sebenico, Giorgio da Sebenico (Box 4)
- Silvestro Dell'Aquila (Box 4)
- Folder 1: Miscellaneous photographs of Italian Renaissance sculpture, some related to Charles Seymour, Jr., Sculpture in Italy: 1400-1500 (Pelican History of Art) (Box 5)
- Folder 2: Miscellaneous photographs of Italian Renaissance sculpture, some related to Charles Seymour, Jr., Sculpture in Italy: 1400-1500 (Pelican History of Art) (Box 5)
- Folder 3: Set of mounted photographs of Italian Renaissance sculpture, some related to Charles Seymour, Jr., Sculpture in Italy: 1400-1500 (Pelican History of Art) (Box 5)
- Folder of miscellaneous 16th-century sculpture and painting (Box 6)
- Folder of miscellaneous 15th and 16th-century sculpture and diagrams related to Charles Seymour, Jr., Sculpture in Italy, 1400-1500, Pelican History of Art Series, 1st ed., 1966 (Box 6)
- Italian Renaissance Sculptors and Monuments: (Box 6)
  - Nanni di Banco (Box 6)
  - Berreguete (Box 6)
  - Brunelleschi (Box 6)
  - Benedetto da Maiano (Box 6)
  - Bertoldo (Box 6)
  - Ciuffagni, St. Matthew (Box 6)
  - Donatello, San Lorenzo Pulpit (Box 6)
  - Donatello, Or San Michele (Box 6)
  - Donatello (Box 6)
  - Matteo Civitale (Box 6)
  - Ghiberti, Siena Baptistery reliefs (Box 6)
  - Tullio Lombardo (Box 6)
  - Michelozzo (Box 6)
  - Pellegrini Chapel (Box 6)
  - Luca della Robbia, including line drawings of Florence Cathedral cantoria by Peter W. Milton (Box 6)
  - Rossellino (Box 6)
  - Sangallo (Box 7)
  - Jacopo Sansovino (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Italian Renaissance sculpture (Box 7)
- Baroque and Rococo Sculpture and Painting: (Box 7)
  - Giovanni da Bologna (Box 7)
  - Carpeaux: Drawings, Paintings, Catalog Information (Box 7)
  - Carpeaux: duplicates (Box 7)
  - Carpeaux Problem (Box 7)
  - Clodion (Box 7)
  - Antoine Coysevox (Box 7)
  - Foggini (Box 7)
  - French Baroque: Girardon, La Grand Dauphin (Box 7)
  - Girardon (Box 7)
  - Le Lorrain (Box 7)
  - Rococo: Noiret, Portrait de Louis XIV et das a famille (Box 7)
  - Perino da Vinci (Box 7)
  - Pigalle (Box 7)
  - Germain Pilon (Box 8)
  - Versailles Fountains (Box 8)
- Frick Collection: Baroque, Italian, French, German Schools (Box 8)
- Nineteenth and Twentieth Centuries: Sculptors (Box 8)
- Maillol, bronze figure (Keck Collection) (Box 8)
- Rodin (Box 8)
- Rodin Forgery (Box 8)
- Unidentified (4 folders) (Box 9)
- Sculpture, not identified (Box 9)
- Urbino (Box 9)
- Sculpture, Gothic Italy (Box 9)
- Mounted photographs and diagrams associated with publications (14 items) (Box 9)
- Houdon, photographs and correspondence (Box 10)
- Houdon, General (Box 10)
- Houdon, George Washington (Mt. Vernon) (Box 10)
- Houdon, George Washington (Mt. Vernon), Problem correspondence (Box 10)
- Houdon, George Washington, Problem Notes (Box 10)
- Houdon, Bust of Washington, correspondence related to a possible purchase (Box 10)
- Frick – Houdon problems, correspondence (Box 10)
- Houdon Problem Correspondence (Bronginard Children) (Box 10)
- Knoedler Houdon (Box 10)
- Houdon, Monroe – Photos and Documents (Box 10)
- Michelangelo and the David Theme, typescript marked National Gallery, 4/3/49 (Box 10)
- Collection of photographs illustrating the arrival of Michelangelo's David on loan to the National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C. from the Bargello, Florence, in 1949 (Box 10)
- Illustrations for Charles Seymour, Jr., Michelangelo's David; a search for identity, Pittsburgh, 1967 (Box 10)
- Michelangelo, Doni Tondo (Box 10)
- Michelangelo (Box 11)
  - Folder of photographs, Xeroxes and typescripts related to Michelangelo's Sistine Ceiling (Box 11)
  - Folder of notes and drafts for "New Light on the Imagery of the Sistine Chapel: The Tituli" (Box 11)
  - "Tituli talk", March 1, 1971 (Box 11)
  - Folder of notes and Xeroxes related to the iconography of the Sistine Chapel (Box 11)
  - W.W. Norton correspondence related to Michelangelo's David, Norton Critical Studies series (Box 11)
  - W.W. Norton correspondence and photographs related to Michelangelo's Sistine Ceiling, Norton Critical Studies series (Box 11)
- Vermeer (Box 11)
  - Vermeer, Camera obscura (Box 11)
  - Vermeer, The Courtesan (Box 11)
  - Vermeer, Girl in a Red Hat (Box 11)
  - Dutch Baroque, Vermeer (Box 12)
  - Dutch Baroque, Vermeer, Laughing Girl (Box 12)
  - Dutch Baroque, Vermeer, Woman Weighing Gold (Box 12)
  - Dutch Baroque, Vermeer, Lacemaker (Box 12)
  - Dutch Baroque, Vermeer, Girl with a Flute (Box 12)
- Typescript and illustrations for the article "The Tomb of Saint Simeon the Prophet in San Simeone Grande, Venice" (Box 12)
- Verrocchio (Box 12)
  - Verrocchio/Pollaiuolo, engraving problem (Box 12)
  - Verroccchio, miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Tomb of Giovanni Piero de'Medici (Box 12)
  - Female Portraits (Box 12)
  - Colleoni Monument (Box 12)
  - San Lorenzo, Florence, lavabo (Box 12)
  - San Lorenzo, Old Sacristy, Deacon Saint (Box 12)
  - Eros with a Dolphin (Box 12)
  - Careggi Resurrection (Box 12)
  - Verrocchio, paintings and drawings (Box 13)
  - Verrocchio, Giuliano de'Medici (Box 13)
  - Verrocchio (design only), Lorenzo the Magnificent, National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C. (Box 13)
  - Verrocchio, David (Box 13)
  - Verrocchio, Pistoia, Forteguerri Monument (Box 13)
  - Attributed by Seymour to Verrocchio (Box 13)
  - Verrocchio, Doubting Thomas, detail photographs (Box 13)
- Painting Photographs (Box 13)
  - St. Jerome, Yale (Box 13)
  - Andrea del Castagno (Box 13)
  - Fra Angelico, Rabinowitz Annunciation, Seymour seminar project (1969- 1970), Photographs gift of Flora Clancy (Box 13)
  - Master of Citta di Castello (Box 13)
  - Giovanni di Paolo (Box 13)
  - Piero della Francesca (Box 13)
  - Domenico Ghirlandaio (Box 13)
  - Leonardo da Vinci (Box 13)
  - Ambrogio Lorenzetti (Box 13)
  - Masaccio (Box 13)
  - Raphael (Box 13)
  - Parri Spinelli (Box 13)
  - Titian, Yale University Art Gallery (Box 13)
  - Florentine School, XVth Century (Crucifixion with Saints) (Box 13)
  - School of Ferrara (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous Paintings unidentified (Box 13)
  - Art Dealer's folder of Allegorical Figures by G.B. Tiepolo, from E & A Silberman Galleries, 32 East 57th Street, New York, NY (Box 13)
  - Salviati Portraits, folder of photographs and texts (Box 13)
- Miscellaneous Unidentified Paintings, mostly Italian 15th century (Box 14)
- French Baroque, De La Tour, St. Sebastian Mourned by St. Irene (Box 14)
- Sustermans (Box 14)
- Three Musician Problem (16th-Century Venetian) (Box 14)
- Gordon Moran articles and illustrations (Box 14)
- Gothic or Revival: Some Aspects of Definition of Style in Italian Renaissance Sculpture 1395-1420, typescript, notes, illustrations (Box 14)
- Metalwork (Box 14)
- "A Reconsideration of Yale's MS. 1954.7.1: The Resurrection of Christ and the Three Marys at the Tomb", Craig Alan Monson, Xerox (Box 14)
- Correspondence on paintings and sculpture, seeking the opinions, expertise, etc. of Charles Seymour (Box 14)
- Material related to Mr. Chalfin's Marble Bust (Box 14)
- Mounted photographs of the Porta` della Mandorla, Florence Cathedral (34 items) (Box 15)
- Miscellaneous mounted and unmounted photographs, principally Alinari, related to publications, mostly Charles Seymour, Jr., Sculpture in Italy, 1400- 1500, Pelican History of Art Series, 1st ed., 1966 (Box 16)
- Miscellaneous mounted and unmounted photographs, principally Alinari, related to publications, mostly Charles Seymour, Jr., Sculpture in Italy, 1400- 1500, Pelican History of Art Series, 1st ed., 1966 (Box 17)
- Folder marked "Rossellino" which appears to be related to attribution questions (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous acetate negatives for works of art related to Charles Seymour's areas of research and publication interests, particularly Italian Renaissance materials (Box 18)
- Miscellaneous photographs for works of art related to Charles Seymour's areas of research and publication interests, particularly Noyon Cathedral and other aspects of medieval art and architecture (Box 19)
- Miscellaneous photographs for works of art related to Charles Seymour's areas of research and publication interests, particularly Noyon Cathedral and other aspects of medieval art and architecture (Box 20)
- Miscellaneous acetate negatives for works of art related to Charles Seymour's areas of research and publication interests, particularly Italian Renaissance materials (Box 21)
- Miscellaneous acetate negatives for works of art related to Charles Seymour's areas of research and publication interests, particularly Italian Renaissance sculpture (Box 22)
- Oversized material (26 items) including photographs, photo montages, ground plans, diagrams and drawings mostly related to Noyon Cathedral, and 4 items related to work on the Porta della Mandorla, Florence Cathedral, and Michelangelo studies (Box 23)